The Town by the River (Continued)
（桐山 零(きりやま れい)）まだ 来てないな
It still hasn't come.
（二海堂(にかいどう)晴信(はるのぶ)）フフフ…
Is this what you're looking for, Kiriyama Rei?
お探しのものは こちらかな？
桐山零君
CHUB
ついに
公の場で対局をする日が来たな
Finally, the time has come for us to face off in a public forum.
Creak
Mr. Kiriyama Rei
Match Notification
This came to my house, so I figured you would get one too.
こいつが
我が家にも届いていたから—
Mr. Kiriyama Rei
Match Notification
君の家にも
届いていることだろうと思ってな
こうして やって来たというわけさ
That's why I came over.
I felt I had to deliver this letter to you with my own hands no matter what!
この手紙だけは 是が非でも
我が手で直接渡したいと思ってな
So you opened my mailbox without permission, Nikaidou?
で ポスト開けたんすか？
人んちの勝手に？ 二海堂さん
I've waited for so long.
いやあ 長かった
確かに 貴様より四段入りは
２年ばかり遅れたが—
True, it took me two years longer to reach 4-dan,
but now is where it really begins!
これからが真のスタート
The beginning of true battle!
真の戦いが始まるのだ
You even opened the envelope?!
しかも 封筒開けてるし
犯罪っすよ？
That's a crime, you know!
To think, ever since the day I first played against you at the National Children's Shogi Championship ten years ago,
思えば 10年前の
全日本子ども将棋選手権で
貴様と初めて対局した日から
I decided you'd be my lifelong rival,
and I've worked hard to improve every single day.
俺は貴様を
終生のライバルと決め—
今日まで日進月歩で
努力を重ねてきた
I researched under the moonlight, read books by the light of fireflies,
月の明かりで研究をし
蛍の光で本を読み—
and told myself that I was just a late bloomer!
自分を大器晩成型の人間であると
励ましながらだ
However, in the end, I too am a shogi prodigy...
が しかし
（二海堂）やはり 俺も天才で…
（零）じゃ また対局で
Well, see you at the match. Goodnight.
それじゃ おやすみなさい
Hey!
って！ おい！
Come back!
Bastard!
（二海堂）貴様！
Listen when somebody's talking to you!
人の話を聞け！
That's my line!
それは
こっちのセリフだっつーの！
Take it straight out of my hand!
受け取れよ この手から！
対局通知という名の挑戦状を！
Take this declaration of war in
the form of a match notification!
I'll just call the federation myself for the info!
直接連盟に電話して聞くから
もういいです
Don't ignore me, Kiriyama!
水くさいぞ 桐山！
We're friends, aren't we?!
親友だろ！
Friends?!
親友？
聞いたことないよ そんな話
This is the first I'm hearing of this!
How did you come up with that?!
どっから出たんですか？
That's how it usually goes!
普通そういうもんだろ
We're rivals, we put in effort,
and after overcoming those things,
ライバルとか努力とか そういう
いろんなあれを乗り越えて
in the end...
最後には
お互いバチーンとハイタッチで—
we'll...
high five each other! Like that!
Camaraderie
親友誕生みたいな
Effort
Friends
Go with the flow here!
読めよ 流れを！
少年漫画の定石ですよ
This is the standard for boys' manga!
The main character of an orthodox boys' manga
いや そういう正統派少年漫画の
メインキャラは
wouldn't open somebody else's mail and
appear with a smug expression on his face.
人の手紙 勝手に開封して
キメ顔で出てこないでしょう？
Wait, where's Hanaoka? He's usually with you.
ていうか 花岡(はなおか)さんは？
いつものあの人は
どうしたんですか？
My servant?
うぬ？ じいやか？
He's on vacation.
じいやは 今 グリーン休暇だ
Thank you for always taking good care of the young master.
（花岡）いつも お坊ちゃまが
お世話になっております
In appreciation of his 45 years of service to the Nikaidou family,
我が二海堂家に
勤続45年の感謝を込め—
we gifted him an 80-day cruise around the world.
80日間世界一周の船の旅を
プレゼントした
B
a
-
b
a
m
Ba-baam! Like that.
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
ばば〜んとね
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
B
a
-
b
a
m
Master Harunobu, please take special care of your health until I return.
（花岡）晴信様
この花岡が戻るまで どうか
お体には くれぐれもお気をつけて
80 days?!
80日間も？
Then this strange beast will be loose the whole time?!
てことは
その間 この珍獣が野放しに？
Hey, if I go first in our match,
will you do a one-turn loss bishop exchange opening?
（二海堂）
なぁ 今度の対局だけどさ
お前 後手だったら
一手損角換(いってぞんかくが)わりでくる？
Or a cornering rook opening?
それとも 中座流(ちゅうざりゅう)８五飛(ごひ)？
If you go first, will you do a cheerful central rook opening?
先手だったら ゴキゲン中飛車(なかびしゃ)？
I could tell you, but how would
you know if I was telling the truth?
（零）教えてもいいけど
ほんとかどうか
その辺の判断はどうすんの？
Oh, come on. Don't be so cautious.
（二海堂）
まあまあ そう警戒せずとも
After all, once we start, your strategy will be obvious.
どうせ 始まっちゃえば
すぐ分かることなんだしさ
Then why not keep your eyes peeled
on the day of and confirm it yourself?
（零）だったら 当日—
目かっぴらいて
自分で確かめればいいのでは？
That's different.
そこは それ
I'm just trying to mentally prepare myself.
ほら
心の準備ってのがあるじゃんか
Why do I have to help you with your mental preparation?
（零）何で僕が あんたの心の準備
手伝わなきゃなんないんすか
I don't get it.
意味 分かんないんすけど
ん？ 桐山　この菓子うまいな
Kiriyama, these pastries are delicious.
He's not even listening!
（零）て 聞いてねえし
Help me, Hanaoka!
助けて！ 花岡さん！
The Town by the River
I remember the magic spell
From back when a rainbow stretched across the sky
In an instant, every corner of the world
Took on a brilliant hue
The voice of my heart
Always illuminates the path I need to take
It is because I doubt everything
That I know it to be true
Why does my heart still beat?
Why do my lungs still breathe?
Why is my chest burning with passion?
There's a reason for all of that
And, like the starry sky hidden behind the clouds
Like the ticket to a destination I lost somewhere
Like the history of the world from before I was born
You hold the answer just beyond my reach
If nothing else, I know that all too well
If nobody else, I know that all too well
Akari
I like the river.
（零）川が好きだ
好きなものなんて
そんなにはないけど
There aren't many things that I like,
but when I see a lot of water gathered together,
水がたくさん集まった姿を
見ていると—
I go into a daze as my mind becomes quiet.
ぼーっとして 頭がしんとする
千駄ヶ谷(せんだがや)までなら
地下鉄で１本だけど—
It's only one subway stop to Sendagaya,
but on days I have a match,
I like to look at the river on the way,
対局の日は
川を見ながら向かいたくて—
so I walk to the nearest JR station.
ＪＲの駅まで歩いていく
いろんな橋を渡りながら
I cross various bridges as I go.
It's strangely soothing.
妙に落ち着くのは—
Maybe because when I was young,
I lived in a town surrounded by a river on all sides.
小さいころ 川に囲まれた町に
住んでいたせいかもしれない
Although my memories of that time are faint now.
もう
かすかにしか覚えていないけど
A pro shogi player has 30 to 40 matches per year.
プロ棋士の生活は
対局が年30から40局くらい
And there are title matches other than the class-promotion tournament,
そして 順位戦以外にも
タイトル戦はあり—
most of them in tournaments, so the more you win,
そのほとんどが
トーナメント制で—
勝ち進めば 当然
対局数が増えていく
the more matches you'll play.
If you're one of the best in the country,
you might play 70 to 80 matches a year.
トップクラスであれば—
年間70から80局にもなる
棋士もいる
Today's match is the qualifier for the NHK Cup.
今日の対局は ＮＨＫ杯の予選
テレビ局主催の
このトーナメントは
If I make it past the qualifying round of this TV station-sponsored tournament
予選を突破し 決勝トーナメントに
出場できれば—
and participate in the final tournament,
ＮＨＫ杯という—
then, as you can guess by the name...
その名のとおり—
it'll be broadcast nationwide.
（零）全国中継されるのだ
Please let me win this match and be on TV!
（松本(まつもと)一砂(いっさ)）どうか 見事勝ち抜き
テレビにばっちり映りますように
May I beat my opponent, Kiriyama, with my style of shogi!
今回の対戦相手の桐山を 見事
自分の将棋で下せますように
May I incinerate his amoeba-like textbook play with my burning manly soul!
あいつの
アメーバみたいなベタ読みを—
俺の燃える漢魂(おとこだま)で
焼き尽くせますように
Kiriyama!
桐山！
逃げた？ ねえ 今 逃げた？
Did you run? Did you just try to run?
You know what that is? That's called a "spiritual defeat"!
ねえ 知ってる？
そういうの
気迫負けっていうんだよ
His name is Matsumoto Issa.
（零）彼の名前 松本一砂
Ｃ級２組 26歳 五段
Class C2, 26 years old, 5-dan.
攻撃的な棋風
というか 攻撃しかしてこない
His playing style is aggressive.
In fact, all he does is attack.
He charges at his opponent like a wild boar or a ball of fire.
イノシシか火の玉かってくらいの
突っ込みを見せてくる
Shogi Hall
U-Um...
あ… あの
I-I can't see.
（零）み… 見えない
Wh-What?
な… 何？ こ… 怖い
S-Scary.
I see it!
見えた！
Hey. Knock it off, Icchan.
（三角(みすみ)龍雪(たつゆき)）
ちょっと やめてよ　いっちゃん
びっくりすっからさ
You'll scare me.
Oh, sorry, Smith! I can't help but get carried away!
いやあ すまん スミス
つい気持ちが高ぶってしまってな
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
いいなぁ
お前さんは いつもストレートで
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
I envy how you wear your heart on your sleeve.
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
Tee-hee
Spin
Twitch
でも やめておくれよ
But still, cut it out.
You'll scare me so much that all the pieces in my head could scatter.
びっくりして頭の中の駒
散らばっちゃうからさ
This is Smith.
（零）この人はスミス先輩
Ｂ級２組 六段
Class B2, 6-dan.
In the
kendo club
(almost never
attends)
In the
kendo club
(almost never
attends)
On the volleyball
team (never attends)
It seems they get along well because they're both tall.
大きな生物同士
２人は気が合うらしい
Well?! How's that, Kiriyama?!
どう？ どうよ 桐山きゅん？
Hm?
Huh?
What?
あ… あれ？
Wait, what?
You're dropping a pawn there?
そこに 歩(ふ)？
Huh?
What?
Wait, what?!
If I take it, his horse will pull back a square.
取ると馬が引かれて…
Kiriyama
+B-6f
Matsumoto
P-5g
Kiriyama
N*5e
It's not over yet!
なんの まだまだ
Matsumoto
+G4g-4h
Kiriyama
N-6g+
Matsumoto
L*5h
Kiriyama
S*5i
I-It's not over! It's not over!
ま… まだまっだ　まま…
Not over, over, not, not over!
だまだまだま　だだだままま
Gloom
（三角）あ〜あ
He wanted his grandpa who lives out in the country to see him.
田舎のじいちゃんに
見てほしかったんだよ
His grandpa isn't doing well, so he's in the hospital.
今 体悪くして入院してんだ
If NHK broadcasts it, you can watch from anywhere.
ＮＨＫは
日本全国どこでも映るもんな
When Issa was a kid,
his grandpa taught him how to play shogi.
小さかったころの一砂に
初めて将棋を教えてくれたのが
じいちゃんだったんだよ
Hey, cheer up, Icchan.
な 元気だせよ いっちゃん
ふっ 桐山がおごってくれるってさ
Kiriyama said he'll treat us!
What?!
Don't you wanna see Akari?
あかりさんに会いたくね？
はうっ あかりさん
Akari.
Parallel Displacement (5 cm/s)
Akaaaari!
あかりすわわーん
Why do I have to treat you guys?
何で僕が？ おごり？
It's fine. Besides, what else does a kid have to spend all that money on?
いいの いいの
子どもが金持ってたって
しょうがないでしょ
But I'm still a minor.
それに僕 まだ未成年なんすけど
If you can't drink liquor, they've got soft drinks!
酒がだめでもジュースがあるさ
フルーツもね　高いけどね
Juice too. Although it's expensive!
If Icchan is gloomy, the shogi hall gets gloomy too.
いっちゃんが元気ないと
将棋会館が暗くなっちゃうんだよ
Welcome.
（川本(かわもと)あかり）いらっしゃいませ
まあ 松本さん スミスさん
それに 桐山君も
Oh, Matsumoto and Smith.
And Kiriyama.
A-Akari! Long time no see!
ああ あかりさん
お久しぶりです
どうも　おっ
相変わらず お美しい
Hi there!
Oh, I see you're as beautiful as ever.
（あかり）こちらへどうぞ
Please, have a seat.
Okay!
（松本）失礼します
（三角）ほーい
She's a totally different person here...
（零）何だか 家にいるときと
全然違う人みたいだ
than she is at home.
Maybe it really is a different person.
もしかして
ほんとに違う人だったりして
Here. Orange juice for you, Kiriyama.
はい
桐山君は オレンジジュースね
Oh, thanks.
あ… はい
この間は お菓子包むの
手伝ってくれて ありがとね
Thank you for wrapping the sweets the other day.
（零）いや すみません
やっぱり同じ人でした
I apologize for misleading you.
She's definitely the same person.
Women are amazing.
女の人って すごいな
（松本）ヌフフ…
All right! I feel much better!
よし 元気出てきた！
今日は飲むぞ！
I'm drinking a lot tonight!
桐山君　覚悟しとけよ
お財布の方の
Kiriyama! You better get your wallet ready!
いやっほーい
いいわね 桐山君　今日は
こんなに楽しい先輩たちと一緒で
You're lucky to be in the company of
these fun older guys today, Kiriyama.
They won't force you to drink,
so it's a fun and bright kind of drinking.
無理に飲ませたりしないし
明るくて いいお酒だわ
Of course, I would never force anyone to drink alcohol!
もちろんです
僕はそんなことしません
無理に飲ませたりとか
But you'd apparently force someone to pay for it.
（零）でも
無理にたかろうとしてるんです
You know we're in Ginza, right?
ここ 銀座なんですけど
There are scary older friends too.
怖い先輩もいるもの
The kind that would force you to drink until you black out,
桐山君がつぶれるまで
無理やり飲ませて—
and then abandon you in front of the club.
そのまま
店の前に置き去りにするような
Are you okay? Where are the people you were with?
（あかり）
大丈夫？　一緒の人たちは？
Did they leave you here?
あなた 置いていかれちゃったの？
Here, have some water.
はい お水飲んで
おうちどこ？
Where do you live?
J-June City.
ろ… 六月町(ろくがつちょう)
Oh, that's near my neighborhood.
まあ 近所だわ　私 三月町(さんがつちょう)なのよ
I live in March City.
Can you walk?
（あかり）歩ける？
あ… ちょっと何？
Goodness, you're just skin and bones.
あなた ガリガリじゃない？
Jeez, you probably weigh less than me.
いやね 私より軽いんじゃないの？
When I woke up the next morning, I was in that living room.
（零）翌朝 目を覚ますと
僕は あの居間にいた
Throb
Whirl
Sis, he woke up!
（川本ひなた）
お姉ちゃん　起きたよ
Whirl
Throb
（川本モモ）起きたぁ
He woke up!
Throb
Whirl
U-Um... where am I?
あ… あの… こ… ここは？
Whirl
Throb
おっ 起きたね
おみそ汁 飲むかい？
You're awake, huh?
Want some miso soup?
（零）初めてなのに
なぜか懐かしいあの古い家に…
It was my first time there,
yet something about that old house made me feel nostalgic.
This was my first time meeting the three sisters:
これが 僕とあかりさんの—
そして ヒナちゃんとモモちゃん
３姉妹との出会い
Akari, Hina, and Momo.
These would be the kind of people to go out with.
（あかり）付き合うなら
こういう先輩が一番よ
えっ　つ… 付き合う？
G-Go out with?!
They're kind and reliable.
優しくて 頼もしいもの
はい もちろんです
Yes, of course!
桐山君　何だって僕に頼りたまえ
Kiriyama, you can depend on me for anything!
後輩をいじめたり
あまつさえ たかったりなんて…
Bullying younger guys or sponging off of them...
...is something I would never, ever do! No way!
しません しません
絶対にありえません
Now drink up, Kiriyama!
さあ じゃんじゃん飲みたまえ
桐山君
僕のおごりだ
It's my treat!
Hey, well said. That's the Issa I know!
よし よく言った
それでこそ 一砂だ
Wait, why am I the one treating?!
って あれ？
何で 俺がおごることに？
一砂君に乾杯
A toast to Issa!
Cheers, Kiriyama.
桐山君とも乾杯
（零）ここにいるあかりさんは
いつものあかりさんとは違う
This Akari is different from the Akari at home.
But I think both of them are very beautiful.
でも どっちもとてもきれいだと
僕は思う
Akari
The Other Side of the Bridge
Nothing in here.
何にもない
No bread, no instant noodles, no milk, no water.
パンもカップラーメンも
牛乳も水も
I don't have toilet paper, either.
あ… あとトイレットペーパーも
Oh well. Guess I'll go shopping.
しょうがない 買い物に出るか
There are only warehouses, companies, and factories in June City.
（零）僕の住む六月町は
倉庫と会社と工場ばっかりで
The only way I can get food and daily essentials is by crossing this bridge and going to the supermarket on the other side.
食料品 日用品は
この橋を渡った—
反対側のスーパーに行かないと
手に入らない
I wish there was fast food nearby.
（零）弁当屋が近くにあれば
いいのになぁ
I don't like going by myself to diners and street stalls.
ファミレスとか立ち食いとか
１人で入るの苦手だし
（零）橋を渡った向こう側は三月町
March City is on the other side of the bridge.
That's where Akari and her sisters live.
あかりさんたちの住む町だ
暑い　日陰がない
So hot...
There's no shade.
I-I'm gonna melt.
と… とける
For some time after moving here,
no matter where I walked, it felt like I was in a dream.
（零）この町に越してきて
しばらくの間—
どこを歩いても
夢の中にいるみたいだった
I couldn't hear sounds very well,
and the town seemed to flicker in black and white.
音がよく聞こえないし
町が白黒にチカチカしたりした
But later on I realized that I'd been stressed out.
でも あとで気が付いた
緊張していたのだ
慣れない町に
そして 一人暮らしに
Stressed out about living alone in a town I wasn't used to.
でも…
However...
知ってる人ができた途端—
the moment I met people,
it felt like the other side of the bridge lit up in full color.
橋の向こうに
色が付いたような気がした
They told me to "come over anytime," but did they mean it?
いつでもおいでって
言ってくれたけど ほんとかな
Still, just having a place where I was told to "come over"
to made me happy and my stomach feel full.
何だか おいでと言ってもらえた
場所ができただけで—
その言葉だけで—
うれしくて おなかがいっぱいで
もう十分な気がした
That alone was enough.
（零）あ… 何だろう
What's that?
I smell smoke, like something's burning.
焦げ臭い　煙のにおい　花火？
Fireworks?
いや〜 涼しい
It's nice and cool in here.
Obon Festival Preparation Goods
Obon
Obon Supplies
Oh, that's right.
ああ そっか　お盆か
It's Obon.
（零）えっ
（モモ）零ちゃん 見っけ
I found Rei!
あっ モモちゃん？
Momo?!
Oh, it's Rei!
あ〜 零君だ
Oh, are you shopping?
あらあら お買い物？
ふふーん　カップ麺と菓子パンね
Instant noodles and sweet buns, huh?
I invite you over to eat, but you haven't been coming.
食べにおいでって言っても
来ないしな
はぁ そっか
I see.
桐山君は
私とヒナが作った料理より—
So he prefers instant noodles over the food Hina and I cook.
カップ麺の方が おいしいのか
I'm kinda shocked.
何かショックだね お姉ちゃん
I did my best making the rice balls.
ヒナ おにぎりとか
頑張ったんだけどな
N-No, I... U-Um...
えっ！ ち… 違いま… あの…
（モモ）きゃー 逃げちゃだめなの
Don't run away!
Um...
あの…
Uh... it's not like that...
えっと そうじゃなくって
I... um...
俺は その…
Here, hold this.
はい これ持って
What?
There's a limit of three to a customer.
（あかり）
お１人様３点限りなのよ
This is what we wanted to buy.
今日はこれを買いたくて来たの
うちは 夏の間
おそうめん大量に消費するから
We eat a lot of cold noodles in the summer.
By the way, this is what we're having tonight.
ちなみに 今夜はこれ
零君　から揚げは好き？
Do you like fried chicken?
Y-Yes, I do.
す… 好きです
Then come over.
じゃあ おいで　一緒に食べましょ
Let's eat together.
Okay.
（零）はい
For some reason, I can't say no to Akari.
（零）僕は あかりさんに
何となく逆らえない
Try to vomit. You'll feel better after.
吐いちゃいなさい 楽になるから
What, you don't know how to throw up?
（あかり）
何？ 吐き方知らないの？
Well, all right.
しかたないなあ
Don't bite my finger now.
指かまないでね
ちょっと失礼
Pardon me.
（零）うっ
（あかり）はい
There.
よしよし 上手上手
There, there. You did good.
She saw exactly how pathetic I was from the start,
（零）最初に 一番
みっともないところを—
全部見られてしまったから
もう取り繕えないのだ
so I couldn't keep up any appearance.
Hello.
（あかり）こんにちは おばちゃん
Do you still have hemp twigs?
麻の枝 まだある？
I sure do.
（花屋のおばさん）はいよ
Are you just starting? The sun's about to set.
これからかい？
日が暮れちゃうわよ
Yes.
そうなの
お買い物 長引いちゃって
Shopping took a little longer than expected.
Let's hurry.
急ごう
思ったより遅くなっちゃった
It's later than I thought.
Yeah.
Hina, can you get the baking pan?
（あかり）
ヒナ　ほうろくのお皿持ってきて
あと マッチも
The matches too.
Okay.
It's lit.
（ひなた）あっ ついた
（モモ）あ…
No, no. Don't touch it, Momo.
（あかり）
こら　触っちゃだめよ モモ
Oh, that's right.
（零）ああ そうか
このにおいだったんだ
This was the smell.
It was all throughout the town.
町じゅうに あふれていたのは
Horsies?
（モモ）お馬さん？
That's right. Mom and Grandma rode that to get back home.
（川本相米二(そめじ)）そうだ
これに乗って帰って来たんだ
ばあばも母さんもな
そうか 分かんないか
Well, you might not understand yet.
It's okay. It's hard to understand.
だよな 分かんないよな
But this is what we do.
でも こうすんだよ
My grandma and my mom,
all the way down the line, all did this.
じいちゃんのばあちゃんも
母さんもずっと—
みんなこうやってきたから
これでいいんだ
This is how it should be.
（クロちゃん）あなたですか？
Is it you? Are you giving us food today?
今日は あなたが
くださるんですか？
Hurry up! And a little more than usual, please!
（ミケちゃん）早く！
そして 少しでも多めに！
坊主のご両親のお墓は
どこなんだ？
Where are your parents buried, kid?
あ… 長野です　父の実家がある
In Nagano.
That's where my dad grew up.
I see. That's far away.
そうか　遠いな…
All right, dinner's ready.
さあ ごはんできましたよ
Well, let's eat.
（相米二）おう　じゃあ 食おうか
おお うまく揚がってるな
You did a good job frying it.
Hina did the frying this time.
今日は ヒナが揚げたのよ
I see.
そうか
油はねた ここ
The oil spattered on me right here.
Uh-oh. Well, we did fry it twice.
あらあら 二度揚げしたからね
That's no good.
そりゃいかん 軟こう塗っとけ
Rub some ointment on it.
There's some in one of my drawers.
じいちゃんの引き出しに
入ってっから
There's no reminiscing or anything during dinner.
（零）
思い出話も何もなく 夕げは進む
The wounds are probably still too fresh—
not even dry yet—and they're here in this house.
きっとまだ 傷は生のまま乾かずに
この家に横たわっている
What was it like for me?
僕のときは どうだったっけ？
When did I stop crying?
泣きやんだのは いつだっけ？
How long did it take me to regain my composure?
落ち着いたのは
どれくらいたってだっけ？
変なんだ　思い出せない
It's strange. I can't remember.
I've been in a daze for a while.
ずっと ぼんやりしている
I've been in a daze ever since that day.
あの日から ぼんやりしたまま—
I couldn't find anything else to do.
他にすることが見つからなくて
見つからなくて
Nothing else.
When I left, Akari put the leftover rice and
chicken into containers and gave them to me.
帰り際 あかりさんが
ごはんとから揚げを詰めて
持たせてくれた
Be sure to put them in the fridge when you get home.
（あかり）
帰ったら すぐ冷蔵庫に入れてね
Reheat them in the microwave when you eat them.
食べるときはチンしてね
Come over again on Monday, after your match.
月曜の対局が終わったら
また おいで
That's the last day of Obon, so I'll make plenty of food.
ちょうど 送り盆なの
ごちそう作るし…
Having company over...
誰かいてくれた方が
"...will be a good distraction."
（零）気が紛れるからと—
That's what I thought I heard Akari say,
あかりさんが
言ったような気がしたけど—
小さすぎて よく聞き取れなかった
but her voice was so soft that I couldn't hear clearly.
On the way home, the wind was strong on the bridge,
帰り道 風の強い橋の上—
but the leftovers I held against my stomach were warm,
like a small animal.
おなかに抱えた弁当が—
まるで 小さな生き物のように
あったかかった
The Other Side of the Bridge
Like a resplendent meteor shower
Your words enter my ears and catch fire
They come together like a school of fish
And form a warm corner in my once chilly bosom
As I stood in place, not knowing the right way to reach out
Your hand reached out to touch mine
And no matter how many nights may pass
That warmth still lingers and pulses within
Your very presence shines a bright light on every part of my life
Your racing heartbeat resonates with my frozen heart and sets it ablaze
Before long, the fire dies out
Leaving just one smoldering ember
Which remains with me and won't ever go away
Living inside of me in a place closest to my heart
Next Episode Preview
Episode 3
（松本）お前のライバルが
すばらしい気迫で待ってるぞ
Your rival is waiting for you
with incredible vigor!
You're late, Kiriyama!
I got tired of waiting for you.
（二海堂）遅いぞ 桐山
待ちくたびれたぞ
Excuse me, but is the air
conditioning working?
（零）すいません
空調 効いてますか？
Let's continue!
（二海堂）続けようぜ
It's practically Heaven compared to the roof of that department store.
あのデパートの
屋上に比べたら天国だ
The last piece of fried chicken...
（零）から揚げ 最後の１個
Illustration: Kondou Aki
Three, two, one...
（あかり）せーの
Please look forward to the next episode of
"March comes in like a lion"!
（あかり･ひなた･モモ）
３月のライオン
次回もお楽しみに
（あかり）ご期待くださいね
We hope you watch it!